Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Office Files of Margaret Wilkerson FA1832
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF), Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Office Files of Margaret Wilkerson
1989-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Wilkerson, Margaret B. (1938-)
FA1832
6.07 Cubic Feet 16 document containers: 14 letter boxes, 1 legal box, and 1 oversize box
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2020 and 2021 in three different sets of records and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2020:021, Accession 2020:023, and Accession 2021:004.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement
Collection consists of 1 series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1989-2007
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files Margaret Wilkerson created when she worked at the Ford Foundation, overseeing grant programming for arts, education, culture, and media. Materials in the collection carry though from when Wilkerson joined the Foundation as a Program Officer in the Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC), Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC), to her becoming Director of MAC, to the reorganization of the Foundation's arts and culture programming and installation of MAC in the Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) between 1998 and 2007. They primarily document Wilkerson's review and support of grantee organizations and her participation and leadership in MAC's and the larger Foundation's program strategy and initiatives.
Common materials formats found within the collection include correspondence, meeting notes, drafts, reports, meeting materials, and CDs.
Ford Foundation; Affirmative action programs in education; Art -- Study and teaching; Public broadcasting
- Subject files, 1989-2007; 1; 6.07 Cubic Feet 16 document containers: 14 letter boxes, 1 legal box, and 1 oversize box
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of subject files created by Margaret Wilkerson during the time she worked at the Ford Foundation between 1998 and 2007. The files document her activities through her tenures as Program Officer in the Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC), Media, Arts and Culture unit (MAC), Director of MAC, and Director of MAC within the reorganized Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF).
  Wilkerson's responsibilities for reviewing and supporting grants related to art, education, culture, and media are documented in proposals, evaluations, correspondence, reports, brochures and other promotional materials. Much of Wilkerson's correspondence is between her and grantee organizations and between her and other Ford Foundation staff members in the Foundation's education and culture program areas. Wilkerson was supported in her work by her assistant Audrey Simon.
  A significant number of files in the series pertain to Wilkerson's attendance and support of different convenings and trips. These files contain materials such as agendas, drafts, and notes. The convenings and trips were related to grantee organizations as well as the Foundation's internal meetings for program strategy. One of the Foundation's internal initiatives that many of Wilkerson's files concern centered around affirmative action. There are several publications in the series about affirmative action research.
  - 2004 Program Leadership Meeting, 2003-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2003 Program Leadership Meeting, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The American Assembly meeting, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Public Radio International (PRI) meeting, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Media Big Bet, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Youssou N'Dour Foundation, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Media Big Bet, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Program Associates biographies 2000-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The State of Public Radio: A Report to the Ford Foundation, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Program Associates Orientation Guidelines, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Kenya trip, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Replenishing Democracy - Student proposals, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Strengthening Our Attention to Democracy: Recommendations from Foundation Staff, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Advisors' Meeting transcription, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Public Radio International (PRI) Annual Report, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Museum of Afro-American History, 2001-2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - C Fonds - Sahel Opera Project, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The World Cultures Yearbook 2007 - Cultures, Conflict, and Globalization, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Guggenheim Museum proposal, 1989-2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Media conference - Strengthening Public Media, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The American Assembly - Creative Campus, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ford Foundation Task Force on Pluralism - Diversity in the Grant-making of the Ford Foundation, 2005 March 7 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Michael DiGregorio Program Officer memo - Grant making in Vietnam, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Vietnam visit - Ford Foundation Office for Vietnam and Thailand Briefing Book, 1999-2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Bay Area Video Coalition (BAVC) - Technology Reader, 2000 October 2 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Arts Education Research Convening transcription Job 1 of 2, 2002 April 26 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Arts Education Research Convening transcription Job 2 of 2, 2002 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - ENACT, 1997-2002 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Project Peace: The ENACT Youth Peace Project, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - Constituents of Change: Community organizations and public education reform, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - OMG Center for Collaborative Learning, circa 1998-2005 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Arts and education program evaluations by Edwin Torres, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - World Cultural Forum (WCF), 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Cyrus Driver meeting - Grant proposals, 2002-2003 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Arts for learning: A resource for using the performing, visual and literary arts in your classroom!, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Arts in Education: Bringing the World Into Your Classroom, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Ford Foundation Office of the Vice President Arts Education Fund, 2002 March 28 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Learning and the Arts, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Arts education, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Arts Education Partnership - Third Space: When Learning Matters, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Affirmative Action Roundtable, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Affirmative Action Roundtable, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Affirmative Action Funds - Justice and Journalism Project, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Summary of Convening on African American Studies, 2005 July 14 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - American University Center for Social Media - Public Media ThinkTank Meeting, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Harvard University The Civil Rights Project - College Access Trend Information, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Harvard University The Civil Rights Project, 2001-2005 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Diversity Challenged: Evidence on the Impact of Affirmative Action edited by Gary Orfield with Michal Kurlaender, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Appearance and Reality in the Sunshine State: The Talented 20 Program in Florida by Patricia Martin and Edgar K. Lee, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Percent Plans in College Admissions: A Comparative Analysis of Three States' Experiences by Catherine L. Horn and Stella M. Flores, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Who Should We Help? The Negative Social Consequences of Merit Scholarships edited by Donald E. Heller and Patricia Marin, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - State Merit Scholarship Programs and Racial Inequality edited by Donald E. Heller and Patricia Marin, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Academic Medicine - Educational Benefits of Diversity in Medical School: A Survey of Students report, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Reaffirming Diversity: A Legal Analysis of the University of Michigan Affirmative Action Cases, A Joint Statement of Constitutional Law Scholars, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - An Evaluation of The Civil Rights Project, Harvard University - "Research Initiative on Inclusion and Equity in Higher Education", 2003 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - DynaLantic corp. vs. U.S. Department of Defense brief, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Supreme Court of the United States Barbara Grutter v. Lee Bollinger brief, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Education Learning Circle Meeting, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - JusticeMakers: Collaborative Programming on Media and Social Justice, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Request for Learning Funds to Assess Communications Grants Leading up to University of Michigan Affirmative Action Decision, 2004 February 13 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Ford Foundation Request for Proposals - Collaborating for Educational Reform, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Worldwide Meeting, Santa Monica, California, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 61-62)
  - Difficult Dialogue Initiative proposals, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
  - Inter-Program Religion Working Group, 1998-2002 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Religion, Human Rights, and Social Justice Matching Fund, 2002-2003 (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Leveraging Investments in Creativity (LINC) - Artography: Arts in a Changing America, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - The Pew Charitable Trust performing arts meeting, 2000-2003 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Strategy for Impact, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Education, Media, Arts, and Culture Program (EMAC) Worldwide Meeting, Salvador, Bahia, Brazil, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Arts and Culture Field Discussion - Discussion materials, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - National Conference for Media Reform briefing kit, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Ford Foundation Grant Makers Orientation Diversity Session, 1986-2000 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - I'll Meet You Halfway: The Media and the Public, 2002 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - MIFTAH The Palestinian Initiative for the Promotion of Global Dialogue and Democracy, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Joint Program Worldwide Meeting Planning Survey, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Theater Communications Group, Inc. (TCG), 2000-2002 (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - History of African Americans and Communism, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - American Indian Higher Education Consortium (AIHEC), 1999-2002 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - African Diaspora Research Sources, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Crossing Paths: A Performing Arts Educators Forum, Charlotte, North Carolina, 2001-2003 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Center for Media Education (CME) - Youth Civic Culture, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Center for Media Education (CME) - Civic Media and Youth: Building Social Capital in an Electronic Era, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Center for Media Education (CME) - Research Initiative on Media, Children, and Youth, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Caribbean Cultural Center - African Diaspora Institute, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Boys Choir of Harlem, Inc., 1999-2001 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Individual artists - Institute on the Arts and Civic Dialogue (IACD), 1996-2003 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Rockhopper inquiry and Fund for Community Organizing, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Creative Exchange: The Forum for Cultural Rights Development, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - 651 ARTS, 2001-2002 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Arts and Identity Explorations, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Ford Foundation Office of the Vice President 9/11 Fund, 2001-2003 (Box 8, Folder 92-93)
  - Anne T. Dowling invitation, undated (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Brooklyn Academy of Music (BAM), 1963-2002 (Box 9, Folder 95-96)
  - The Ford Foundation's "Internationalizing New Work in the Performing Arts", undated (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - China trip, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Worldwide Meeting, Beijing, China, 2004-2006 (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, Freedom Program (KCF) Retreat, 2003 (Box 9, Folder 101)
  - A Report on the First-Phase Achievements in the Project for the Construction of Ethnic Cultural and Ecological Villages in Yunnan, China, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 102)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Learning Circle Meeting, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Indonesia Education Statistics, circa 2004 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - El Comercio newspaper, 2006 February 10; File contains a full size newspaper (Box 16, Folder 105)
  - Universidad Nacional de San Antonio Abad del Cusco - Hatun Nan Program, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - New York University - Celebrating Excellence Transforming Lives, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Ford Foundation Trustee Committee visit to Egypt background materials, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Ford Foundation Trustee Committee visit to Egypt briefing book, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - WorldLink TV, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 110)
  - Arts Education Partnership - Critical Links: Learning in the Arts and Student Academic and Social Development, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 111)
  - Americans for the Arts and Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Retreat, 2002-2003 (Box 10, Folder 112)
  - Education and Scholarship Learning Circle Meeting, Cusco and Lima, Peru, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 113-114)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Ford Foundation Trustee Committee visit to Egypt - Preparatory visit, 2006 (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - The Fund for Artists, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Diaspora Music Village Teacher's Pack, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - diaspora Music Village Teacher's Pack CD, 2002 (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - The Center for New Words - Prospectus and Preliminary Business Plan, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Introduction to Ford Foundation reports on African-American studies, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Memoria del Fideicomiso para la Cultura Mexico-EUA (Report of the US-Mexico Fund for Culture), 1999 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Arts and the Islamic World, Volume 35 - Egypt: the arts in view, undated (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - The University of Texas at Austin Department of Radio-Television-Film, 2002 (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - Affirmative action grant materials part 1, 1991-2001 (Box 12, Folder 124-126)
  - Affirmative action grant materials, part 2, 1997-2000 (Box 13, Folder 127)
  - Public Media Foundation - Gary Poon, 1999-2003 (Box 13, Folder 128-130)
  - Center for Progressive Media - Feasibility Study and Business Plan, 2002 November (Box 13, Folder 128)
  - Leveraging Investments and Creativity (LINC), 2002-2003 (Box 14, Folder 131-132)
  - The Partnership for Artists in the 21st Century (PA21), 2002-2004 (Box 14, Folder 133-134)
  - Ford Foundation New Directions/New Donors initiative (ND/ND), 2001-2003 (Box 14, Folder 135)
  - Ford Foundation New Directions/New Donors initiative (ND/ND), 2003 (Box 14, Folder 136)
  - Mural Arts Program of Philadelphia, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 137)
  - Mural Arts Program of Philadelphia - The Map to Hope, 2005 (Box 15, Folder 137)
  - New America Media awards - Jon Funabiki, 2006 (Box 15, Folder 138)
  - Diaspora Vibe Cultural Arts Incubator, 2007 (Box 15, Folder 139)
  - Investing in Media that Matters: A Gathering at Sundance Village, 2002 (Box 15, Folder 140)
  - Knowledge, Creativity, and Freedom Program (KCF) Retreat - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) learning agenda, 2006-2007 (Box 15, Folder 141)
  - Media, Arts, and Culture unit (MAC) Team Development Day, 1999; File contains oversized ephemera (Box 16, Folder 142)